Register of the Edward Geary Lansdale papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Sound Recordings, 1951-1975
  - Music by American servicemen, undated
    - Tape 92, Vietnam, undated
      This is a tape of the "Merrymen," a singing group of men from the 173rd assault helicopter company. The copy is not good.
      - 1. "Hi Johnny, Hi Johnny," Merrymen (English)
      - 2. "Silver Wings," Merrymen (English)
      - 3. "Sky King," Merrymen (English)
      - 4. "Tuyen," Merrymen (English)
      - 5. "Serviceman's Ode," Merrymen (English)
      - 6. "Army Aviation," Merrymen (English)
      - 7. "Black Iron Cross," Merrymen (English)
      - 8. "You Are My Sunshine," Merrymen (English)
      - 9. "Picadilly Square," Merrymen (English)
      - 10. "Airsick Arvin," Merrymen (English)
      - 11. "KUZZ Radio," Merrymen (English)
        An imaginary Arkansas country and western radio station. The songs are satirical and profane, as are the "commercials" and the "interview from Saigon in Vietnamese."
    - Tape 93, Vietnam, undated
      This is another recording of the "Merrymen," labelled "part one."
      - 1. "I May Not Have a Mansion," Merrymen (English)
      - 2. "Green Back Dollar," Merrymen (English)
      - 3. "All My Trials," Merrymen (English)
      - 4. "Chilly Winds," Merrymen (English)
    - Tape 94, Vietnam, undated
      This is labelled "Merrymen, part two."
      - 1. "Baby, the Rain Must Fall," Merrymen (English)
      - 2. (no name), Merrymen (English)
      - 3. "In that Ole Cotton Field Back Home," Merrymen (English)
      - 4. "In the Land of Odom," Merrymen (English)
      - 5. "I'm on My Way," Merrymen (English)
      - 6. "In the Early Morning Rain," Merrymen (English)
      - 7. "You Are on My Mind," Merrymen (English)
      - 8. "Kansas City," Merrymen (English)
      - 9. "Frank and Jesse James," Merrymen (English)
    - Tape 95, undated
      This tape is entitled "Dick Jonas." There is no date. It is a tape of Jonas's country and western music, along with a couple of the "Wolf Pack" numbers heard on an earlier tape (89).
      - 1. "Angelina," Dick Jonas (English)
      - 2. "Henry Jones," Dick Jonas (English)
      - 3. Song about sharecropping, Dick Jonas (English)
      - 4. "Seven Little Chartreuse Men," Dick Jonas (English)
      - 5. "Sadie Belle," Dick Jonas (English)
      - 6. "Seaboard Line," Dick Jonas (English)
      - 7. "Loving Her Was Easier than Anything I'll Ever Do Again," Dick Jonas (English)
      - 8. "Houseboy for the Wolf Pack," Dick Jonas (English)
      - 9. "There's a Fireball Down There on the Hillside," Dick Jonas (English)
      - 10. "My Daddy Died on Normandy Sand," Dick Jonas (English)
      - 11. Drum, bass, and recitation about getting a jet ready to take servicemen home
      - 12. "Like the Sea Meets the Shoreline," Dick Jonas (English)
      - 13. Religious song, Dick Jonas (English)
    - Tape 96, undated
      This is a recording of Sgt. Barry Sadler (most famous for "The Ballad of the Green Beret) singing twelve of his songs. The entire album is recorded twice on this tape. The second side of the tape is blank.
      - 1. "The Ballad of the Green Beret," Barry Sadler (English)
      - 2. "I'm Going Home," Barry Sadler (English)
      - 3. "Oh Lord, I'm Tired and Sad (Letter Postmarked Vietnam)," Barry Sadler (English)
      - 4. "Badge of Courage," Barry Sadler (English)
      - 5. "City on Mekong Shore, Saigon," Barry Sadler (English)
      - 6. "Nurses of Vietnam," Barry Sadler (English)
      - 7. "Watching the Rain Drops Fall," Barry Sadler (English)
      - 8. "Gari-Trooper," Barry Sadler (English)
      - 9. "Green Sod O'er Me," Barry Sadler (English)
      - 10. "Come All Ye Maidens (I Must Go Where Brave Men Die)," Barry Sadler (English)
      - 11. "Ban Moui Ba," Barry Sadler (English)
      - 12. "I'm Going Home," Barry Sadler (English)
    - Tape 97, undated
      This is entitled "Vietnam: Songs of the Grunt." All songs were written and performed by Bill Ellis (© DeGar Music, ASCAP).
      - 1. "Grunt," Bill Ellis (English)
      - 2. "Firefight," Bill Ellis (English)
      - 3. "Song of the First Cavalry," Bill Ellis (English)
      - 4. "Freedom Bird," Bill Ellis (English)
  - Philippines, 1951-1974, undated
    This is an assortment of tapes from General Lansdale's years in the Philippines, including a recording of a party given for him before he left (tapes 98-99), recordings of Philippine music, and two recordings of the music used by Magsaysay in his campaign for the presidency (tapes 104 and 107).
    - Tape 98, 1954 January 17
      This is a "Despidida for Colonel Lansdale." A group of General (then Colonel) Lansdale's friends gathered at the Manila Overseas Press Club to have a party and say goodbye to him as he was about to leave for other missions. The Mayor of Manilla, Arsenio Laoson, speaks at the beginning of the tape. Ramon Magsaysay (just inaugurated as President of the Philippines) was also present. This recording is continued on tape 99.
      This "Despidida" is recorded on track two only. Track one is a program entitled "Christmas with the Children of New York City."
    - Tape 99, 1954 January 17
      This is a continuation from tape 98. Arsenio Laoson is speaking. Then Colonel Lansdale speaks, very briefly, and says thanks. A friend by the name of Theo Rogers also speaks twice on this tape -- he seems to be having an especially good time. The whole crowd sings "For He's a Jolly Good Fellow." At the end of the tape a voice comes on and lists some "notables" of the 500 people who attended General Lansdale's "Despidida."
      General Lansdale recalls that the Evening News ran a spoof edition for the affair, with the banner headlines warning the Pentagon that Lansdale was on his way home.
      After the Despidida there remains a portion of the program which was recorded on the tape before it was used for the Despidida.
    - Tape 100, undated
      This is a recording of Philippine folk songs and dances. All of the music is instrumental. Although there is a list of song titles on the back of the tape box, it is unclear whether or not this is accurate, as there is also a loose sheet of paper in the box which lists a different set of songs.
    - Tape 101, undated
      This is more music like that on tape 100. Again, there is a list of the song titles, which may or may not be accurate.
    - Tape 102, undated
      This tape is entitled "Pilita -- Philippine love songs, arranged and conducted by D'Amarillo, vocal supervision by Philip Maninang."
      - 1. "Dahil Sa Iyo"
      - 2. "Kay Hirap Ng Unibig"
      - 3. "Carinosa"
      - 4. "Lahat Ng Araw"
      - 5. "Hinahanap Kita"
      - 6. "Sapagka't Kamil'y Tao Lamang"
      - 7. "Kapantay Ay Langit"
      - 8. "Irog, Ako Ay Mahalin"
      - 9. "Rosas Pandan"
      - 10. "Lahat Ng Oras"
      - 11. "Sapagka't Ikaw Ay Akin"
      - 12. "Lihim Na Damdamin"
    - Tape 103, undated
      This tape contains more Philippine folk songs, like those on tapes 100 and 101.
    - Tape 104, undated
      This is "Old Philippine records -- Includes Magsaysay Mambo." The first two songs are the Mambo and "Magsaysay March," both of which were political jingles in the Philippines during Magsaysay's election campaign. The songs are in English and Tagalog. The rest of the tape contains more Philippine folk songs, including some choral music.
    - Tape 105, undated
      This tape contains more Philippine folk music, like tapes 100, 101, and 103.
    - Tape 106, undated (Box 92)
      This tape is entitled "Harana Ni Ruben Tagalog." It is a recording of a male singer performing what sounds like Philippine popular music.
    - Tape 107, circa 1951
      This tape is a letter from General Lansdale to his wife, Helen. It was recorded in 1951, and a copy was made in 1953. General Lansdale and his friends sing and give personal news. After the letter, General Lansdale has recorded two Philippine campaign songs: "Magsaysay Mambo" and "Magsaysay March," both in support of Magsaysay. The songs are sung both in English and in Tagalog.
    - Tape 108, 1974 September
      This is a tape of the "Madrigal singers of the University of the Philippines at the Magsaysay Awards." Eight songs are sung; all except for the first one are in Tagalog.
  - Miscellaneous music, 1963, undated
    This group includes tapes of the U.S. Army Band (109-110), "Spanish-Latin music" (111-114), and the Mexican Navy Quintet (115).
    - Tape 109, United States, undated
      This is a recording of the U.S. Army Band, W. O. Kinney, conductor. This tape is labelled "part one." There are nine songs recorded; titles are not provided. This recording is continued on tape 110.
    - Tape 110, United States, undated
      This is a continuation from tape 109: U.S. Army Band, part two. Five songs are recorded; the fourth is an instrumental version of "Vietnam, Vietnam," by General Lansdale's friend, the Vietnamese songwriter Pham Duy.
    - Tape 111, undated
      Spanish-Latin music.
      Tapes 111-114 are all "Spanish-Latin music" recordings. They appear to be recordings of music from various Latin American countries. It cannot be determined where or when the tapes were made, but the first one (111) has "April 11, 1963" printed on it.
      This tape is entitled "Concierta en la Llanura--musica tipica Venezoland. Los Torrealberos Al Arpa: Juan Vicente Torrealba."
    - Tape 112, undated
    - Tape 113, undated
    - Tape 114, undated
      This tape also has the following printed on it: "Music of Bolivia, # 1-12; Music of Paraguay, # 1-12; Music of Guatemala, # 1-6."
    - Tape 115, United States, 1963 June 10
      This is a recording of the Mexican Navy Quintet, the "Conjunto de Cuerdas." The group performs eight numbers while on a tour of the United States. [See also: Lansdale papers, OFFICE FILES FROM THE UNITED STATES DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE, OFFICE OF THE SECRETARY OF DEFENSE/Subject file/Mexican Navy Quintet]
  - Combat, 1968, undated
    The first of these tapes was recorded during an incident in Saigon near the "Brinks," the principal U.S. officers' compound. The second is a recording of a radio operator attempting to direct some units during the Tet offensive.
    - Tape 116, Vietnam/Korea, undated
      This tape begins with a Voice of America correspondent in Korea (Robert Lasher) broadcasting a special report on parachute jumps. Next on the tape is a recording of the famous Bill Cosby routines, "Noah" and "A Flip of the Coin."
      Third on this tape is a recording of an incident on May 10th of an unspecified year. The tape was made by a correspondent who was staying at the Caravelle Hotel in Saigon. Hearing gunshots in the street, the correspondent had rushed out to see what was going on and to record the incident. Across the street from the hotel was the "Brinks," a U.S. officers' compound which had been bombed once by the Viet Cong. It had been rumored that the Viet Cong were about to attack again, and on this particular morning the police and others thought they saw a Viet Cong squad in a car trying to crash into the entrance of the Brinks. The police opened fire in the midst of the morning rush hour. There is the sound of explosions and weapons, and a description by the correspondent of the action taking place. Later, the wounded are carried away and pass near the microphone. The voices of those hurt and the medics caring for them are heard. This incident turned out to be a false alarm: there were no Viet Cong.
    - Tape 117, Vietnam, 1968 January 1
      This is a tape recorded in Saigon during the Tet offensive. The recording begins at 0440 (4:40 a.m.). It was taped by Admiral Veth, who turned on his recorder while listening to the "net" for the troops protecting the U.S. Embassy from the Viet Cong, who had attacked. One individual on the tape provides communication among several different units. He attempts to guide a truck trying to bring in ammunition, directs a helicopter which is dropping flares, and tries to get an ambulance to the wounded. The recording is on both sides of this tape. A partial transcript accompanies this tape and is included in Appendix G.
  - Speeches, seminars, panels, and interviews, 1954-1971, undated
    These tapes include speeches by General Lansdale, panels and seminars in which he participated, and classes he taught. There are also some recordings of speeches by others who mention General Lansdale and his work.
    - Tape 118, United States, undated
      This is a recording of a speech by General Lansdale, entitled "The Communist Way."
    - Tape 119, United States, undated
      This is a tape of a radio program in which General Lansdale took part. The program is entitled "This Shrinking World," and it is a series of editorials based on American foreign aid and the mutual security program. This series is (or was) broadcast by an NBC affiliate, WRC (location unknown). This particular segment of "This Shrinking World" takes the form of a panel discussion with former American Ambassador to Turkey George McGee, now a member of the Draper Committee; the Financial Minister from the British Embassy; and Assistant to the Secretary of Defense Colonel Edward Lansdale. There are two journalists/commentators.
      The discussion begins with a comparison of British and American foreign aid to poorer countries. Each commentator seems anxious to establish which nation, the U.S. or Great Britain, gives more aid. The type of aid given to the various recipients is discussed, and it is agreed that it is futile to give economic aid without also giving military aid (for security). The type of aid given by the U.S.S.R. is discussed, and it is agreed that the Soviets give aid in order to dominate. Soviet "economic warfare" is mentioned and discussed. The panel also talks about the attitudes of the people of the nations giving aid, and those of the people receiving the aid.
    - Tape 120, Philippines, 1954
      This is a recording of a talk given by Lansdale to a military audience in the Philippines. His subject is the war in Indochina. Lansdale hopes to interest his audience in this topic because of the proximity of Vietnam to the Philippines. He begins with a history of Vietnam, from the colonial period on, to explain why and how the French come to be involved in this war. He discusses Ho Chi Minh and describes him as a "professional revolutionary" educated, in part, in Moscow. He emphasizes that many "regular" (governmental) armed forces in Vietnam have voluntarily joined the French against Ho Chi Minh's forces. He finally points out that the Viet Minh are advised by at least 2,000 Chinese Communists and draws an analogy with the Japanese invasion during World War II: first Vietnam, then Thailand, Burma, Malaya, Indonesia, and finally the Philippines fell to foreign domination. After General Lansdale's talk there are questions and comments from the audience.
    - Tape 121, United States, 1959 June (Box 93)
      This is a tape of a portion of the 12th annual conference of the Military Government Association, held in Washington, D.C. A speaker calls the meeting to order and introduces the chairman of the first panel, the topic of which is "International Military and Political Affairs." The chairman, who is a past president of the Association, is Brig. General Strom Thurmond. Thurmond introduces each panel member as they present their talks. Below is a list and a synopsis of what each has to say.
      The Honorable John Erwin II, Assistant Secretary of Defense, was supposed to have given a talk but was unable to attend. His deputy, Robert H. Knight, took Erwin's place. Knight reviews the strength of the military of Communist states and the uses to which the military is put. According to Knight, the Communists use their military to control others, to supply arms to small countries, to take over small countries, and to provide self-defense in the event of war (including an accidental war). Knight also reviews the strength of the U.S. and other free-world military forces.
      Brig. General Millard C. Young, Air Force, from the Office of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, covers the topic of personnel and planning for cold war activities. Before he begins he mentions that he feels "timid before such outstanding company as General Lansdale." He discusses the "state" of cold war and the psychological preparedness of the Communists. He argues that Americans, military and non-military, must "put on our cold war glasses" to see reality, and we must "keep them on all the time." He further argues that to successfully combat Communist propaganda against us (which makes us unpopular in the countries we are trying to help), we must send to trouble spots people who know the language and the customs of the host population.
      The Honorable Robert D. Murphy, Undersecretary of State, is given the topic of the "international political situation." He decides to discuss the Berlin situation, "as it relates to the present talks going on in Geneva." Murphy outlines the plan offered by the U.S., which includes reunification of Berlin as the prospective capital of a reunited Germany; free elections; agreed-upon reduction of forces (by all four powers) in both Germanys; measures to prevent Germany from becoming aggressive; and a democratic government for the reunited Germany.
      Colonel Edward Lansdale, Deputy Assistant to the Secretary of Defense for Special Operations, speaks on "cold war and civil affairs." General Lansdale touches on the basic differences between Communist thought and American thought, and he discusses "the little people" who must deal with Communists in their own country. He outlines the reaction of the people of the Philippines to the Communist Huks, and the difference in morale made by the institution of free elections. He concludes by stressing that the U.S. must hold fast in the fight for freedom, because it is our bond with "men of good will, everywhere."
      Richard M. Helms covers the fifth topic, "Soviet military occupation." Helms is the Assistant Director of the CIA. His talk is a review of history, concentrating on the way the U.S.S.R. tried to rule (and usually succeeded) in four countries: Austria, East Germany, Poland, and Hungary. He discusses the way the people of these countries resisted Soviet repression of their freedoms (of press, speech, and assembly). He then describes how the Soviets were able, more often than not, to crush any resistance.
    - Tape 122, United States, 1966 September 25
      This is a recording of the dedication ceremonies for the Freedom Studies Center of the Institute for American Strategy at Boston, Virginia. The U.S. Navy Band plays, and a number of people speak, each of whom was limited to two minutes. The Center is dedicated to studying Communist cold-war tactics and to protecting the American process of government and the American way of life. It is a school of "psycho-political warfare" which is funded privately and administered by the Institute for American Strategy. One of the speakers, Adm. Felix B. Stump (Navy, ret.), mentions that General Lansdale will be the administrative director of the Center. Below is a list of speakers.
      Sen. Harry Flood Byrd, Jr. (D-Va); John O. Marsh, Jr., Virginia congressman; John M. Fisher, President of Insitute; Dr. James D. Atkinson, Georgetown University; Alan G. Grant, originator of the academy; Dr. Walter H. Judd, Board of Directors; Sen. Thomas Dodd (R-Ct), Board of Directors; Adm. Burke, Georgetown University; Kenneth D. Wells, Jr., Freedom Foundation; Dr. L. E. Dubrionski, Captive Nations Committee; John W. Piercy, State Department; Lt. Gen. J. L. Stockmorton, Army; Rear Adm. James F. Calbert, Navy; Lt. Gen. Jack G. Merrill, Air Force; Brig. Gen. Earl E. Anderson, Marine Corps; Adm. Felix Stump, Navy, retired; William C. Darby, Institute for Free Labor; Andrew A. Pettis, AFL-CIO; John C. Frame, Mutual Broadcasting Company; Chauncy Facell, Florida representative; Dr. Woodrow W. Wilkinson, Virginia school system; Nat. Commander John E. Davis, American Legion.
    - Tape 123, United States, 1970 January 16
      COIN course lecture. This lecture was the final class of a course preparing students to handle matters of "insurgency and counterinsurgency." Some of the students were evidently bound for Vietnam. The speaker is Dr. Walter H. Judd, an expert on U.S. foreign policy who served in Congress for Minnesota's 5th District and also acted as a delegate to the World Health Association of the U.N. Dr. Judd lived in mainland China for ten years as a medical missionary under Communist rule.
      The theme of Dr. Judd's lecture is that communism is an international, not a national, movement. "There is on this planet an organized, world-wide movement with the avowed objective and the unwavering will and the steadily-increasing capability to impose its rule on the rest of the world, including the United States." He scorns those who believe that communism is "mellowing" or "maturing." He gives many examples of ways that the U.S.S.R. could lesson world tensions, but it does not do any of these things. Judd argues that the disagreement between the Chinese and Soviet Communists is a struggle within the Party, not between two parties. He emphasizes that it is important to recognize these facts about the Communists, if we are to defeat them.
      He further argues that individual Communist leaders, such as Ho Chi Minh, are not dedicated to the well-being of their own people but rather to the international movement. The war in Vietnam is not, then, simply a civil war and not a war of liberation. According to Judd, the U.S.S.R. wishes to embarrass the U.S. in Vietnam. Because Communist leaders view international communism as an inevitability, and as the only way to achieve world peace, the U.S. is seen as an obstacle. Communist leaders use war, diplomacy, and tricks (Judd gives examples of each of these) to advance their cause. The U.S. should not expect the Communist leaders to grant concessions, Judd says, or to meet it halfway, and the U.S. should not be surprised when the Communists act with treachery. The Communists see themselves as engaged in total war. Judd concludes that the U.S. must learn to engage in total war -- economic, social, educative, athletic, artistic, etc. -- if it is to successfully deal with them. Eventually, Judd says, the U.S. can outlast the Communists. The Communist movement will die out because of internal contradictions and because of the cruelty of its system of government.
    - Tape 124, United States, 1971 October 8
      Use copy reference number: 80116_a_0000247_a01
      This is a recording of an informal interview of General Lansdale by a person -- probably a journalist -- whose name is not given. The interviewer is gathering information about the Vietnam War. At the start, however, the two men talk about a special program that NBC wants to air based on the Pentagon Papers. NBC wants to interview General Lansdale, which he agrees to do if NBC will, in turn, make some copies of some of Lansdale's tapes. The tapes he needs evidently include some of Pham Duy's music, and General Lansdale hopes that the producer will be interested in it.
      Pham Duy "just showed up here in the U.S." with a group of classical musicians. He will be taping music at the University of Southern Illinois (at Carbondale), which has a Center for Vietnamese Studies (a Mr. H. B. Jacobini is Pham Duy's contact there).
      Next the book General Lansdale has written is mentioned. It is to be released in February of 1972. Mme. Nhu has also written a book, and the two men discuss Mme. Nhu for a few minutes.